John, before you join the CIA, you knew
how the game works. You knew how
dangerous it was and actually how
countries play. You had a family as
well. What made you put everything on
the line? I had just finished a tour in
Athens where I was the subject of an
assassination attempt. When I first
arrived in Pakistan, I declined the gun
cuz I was afraid that I would just kill
somebody.
When Bill Clinton was elected, we were
told every recruited asset who had a
problem with human rights was to be
fired. And they went through and fired
fully 1/3 of all of the recruited assets
in the CIA.
If you want to know what the communists
are doing, you're going to recruit
members of the right-wing death squads.
Sometimes members of those death squads
kill Catholic nuns or massacre villages.
All of that changed on September 11th
and it went back to what it was during
the battle days.
>> John, before you join the CIA, you knew
how the game works. You knew how
dangerous it was and actually how
countries play. You had a family as
well. What made you put everything on
the line? Well,
I'm not sure I can give you a direct
answer. When when I was 9 years old, I
told my parents that I wanted to be a
spy when I grew up. And they humored me
by buying me, you know, walkie-talkies
that kids get when they're little and
disappearing ink, you know, and things
like that. But when I was 16, I told my
father that I wanted to be a spy in the
Middle East specifically. And then I
went to school to study Middle Eastern
uh Middle Eastern studies.
Islam, oil, things like that. So,
I I don't really know if it was one
specific thing that made me want to do
this. I never really thought about the
danger. Even though before I went to the
CIA, I
met casually with people who were in the
CIA to talk about what they did and what
different components of the agency did.
The The danger never really registered
with me until 9/11.
For me, it was all,
you know, fun and games for the most
part.
>> But even still, you you had a family at
the time, right? Yes. But just the sheer
fact of joining the CIA and working
either A as a spy or in counterterrorism
units comes with inherent danger. Yes. I
mean, did that ever cross your mind? No,
because, you know, when you're in your
20s or 30s, you think that you're
indestructible.
And uh and and looking back, I did think
I was indestructible. I remember when I
got back from Pakistan, my mother asked
me if I was afraid, and I said, "No."
Now that I think about it, no. She said,
"Really? Why?" And I said, "Because I
was so busy
that it just never occurred to me to be
afraid."
You know? And and I wasn't armed for the
most part in in Pakistan.
I had just finished a tour in Athens,
where I was the where I was the subject
of a of an assassination attempt. And I
was still a little rattled PTSD-wise
from my tour in Athens. And I declined
the the gun when I first arrived in
Pakistan because I was afraid that I
would just kill somebody.
And so um
I thought just better to not have a gun
because everybody around me was armed.
So, if there's going to be a shootout,
well, you know, I'm going to just hope
for the best and hope that my colleagues
can take care of me. When we went out
for the Abbottabad raids, of course, I I
was armed, but it took me a couple of
months to ease into that.
>> Isn't that part of the job?
Yeah, it is part of the job. And I
remember a colleague of mine kind of
tapping me on the chest and saying,
"Come on, let's go." And then he said,
"Hey, you where's your bulletproof
vest?"
And I said, "Oh, I
I didn't put it on.
I said, I hate the way it it feels and I
said, it's 100° outside and it's going
to make me sweat and be dehydrated. I
just hate it.
And he's like, are you crazy? And I
said, but I don't have a gun on me
either.
So, I don't know. Like I say, you're
just kind of counting on your colleagues
to
cover you for the for the evening.
And what did you think you were joining
when you first joined? I mean, what were
your motivations? They must have been
some preconceived ideas that you had.
Sure, but I but I felt very confident
that this was not the CIA of the 1960s
and early 1970s. So,
when I when I joined, before I joined,
I had dinner one night with
the the boyfriend of a school
uh
fellow student in graduate school.
And her boyfriend was working had worked
for the agency for three or four years
and
he knew I was pretty advanced in the
hiring process and so we got together
for dinner, the three of us. And I was
asking him, you know, well, what about
MK Ultra? What about,
you know, assassinations? What And and
he said, all of that has changed since
1975. All of it has changed. We we
seriously don't do that anymore. And he
was telling me the truth. That truth
lasted from 1975,
well, legally until September 11th, but
it started to decline under William
Casey in the 1980s during the Reagan
administration, you know, Iran-Contra,
for example.
Uh and uh
and uh cocaine
uh that ended up in Los Angeles. So, it
began to change, but but
when when Bill Clinton was elected,
Uh we were told
within the first day or two of the
Clinton administration
that we were going to respect human
rights
and that every recruited asset who had a
problem with human rights was to be
fired.
And they went through and fired fully
1/3 of all of the recruited assets in
the CIA. And I remember saying to a
colleague,
"Wow, Clinton is serious about this.
This really is a different CIA." But
again,
all of that changed on September 11th
and it went back to what it was during
the battle days. Why do you think 1/3
were fired? I mean, when you go through
the recruitment process at the CIA,
you're vetted thoroughly. They look at
every piece of your background. And
also, I'm assuming do tons of
psychological tests and beliefs and lie
detectors and so on and so forth.
Why do you think that 1/3 of the CIA was
had those beliefs?
>> Well, no, it wasn't 1/3 of the CIA. It
was 1/3 of the assets recruited by the
CIA to be informants.
So, listen, if you want to if you want
to know what,
you know, the communists are doing in
the jungles of Colombia,
you're going to recruit members of the
right-wing death squads
that are going after the the
rebels in Colombia. And so, sometimes
members of those death squads kill
Catholic nuns or massacre villages. John
McCain once said, "Never get into a
fight with a pig
because you both get dirty,
but the pig likes it."
And that was the situation that we were
in.
So, the Clinton people came in and said,
"No more
close relationships like this with death
squads, whether it was in Colombia or El
Salvador or Guatemala or whatever."
You know, if we had recruited somebody,
for example like like Manuel Noriega
that was going around killing
communists.
That was the end of the relationship.
Coming back to your CIA
um
recruitment. I mean, what did service
mean to you personally?
Well, I come from an immigrant family.
All four of my grandparents were from
the island of Rhodes in Greece.
And they were so grateful
for the opportunities afforded them here
in the United States
that they always stressed public
service.
And so
when when it came time for me to
graduate from college or from graduate
school
I only considered public service. I only
considered CIA
foreign service, Capitol Hill. That was
it because they instilled in us this
idea that we had to give something back
to this country. And I took that very
seriously. Was there any other way of
giving back? I mean, was that the only
way you saw of giving back or was that
the ultimate way of giving back? Well,
my parents were both elementary school
teachers, public school teachers. And
certainly that's a way of giving back.
Uh my sister went into My sister got a
degree in um
nonverbal communications. So she's ended
up speaking American sign language and
worked with the deaf and things like
that. That was a way of giving back. But
I had such a fascination with
international affairs and especially
with the Middle East
that I wanted to do something
international.
And I had traveled extensively
in college. You know, there's kind of
this
this idea that your junior year you do a
semester abroad, you backpack all around
Europe. I took that very seriously and I
did it multiple times. And I just fell
in love with
you know, travel. It's I I I've never
gotten rid of the travel bug. It sounds
like a
a mix of a travel show and the James
Bond movie, right? So, from when you
were a kid, you had a fascination and
you wanted to be a spy. You then studied
Middle Eastern studies, which gave you
What did it give you? Why Middle Eastern
studies? I mean, did it give you the
love of the history? Did it Was it the
language? Was it the people? From when I
was a kid, I I can't I can't really give
you a straight answer because I'm not
really sure myself what it was. But when
I was a kid, I was absolutely
fascinated by the Middle East. And oddly
enough,
especially fas- fascinated by the
Persian Gulf.
And so, I mean, I was in
I I was given this week-long
scholarship to take a a class at Penn
State University when I was a junior in
high school.
And I went to the university bookstore
uh just to see what these, you know,
college these college kids were reading.
And there were books on the Middle East.
And so, I wasn't in that class, of
course. It was a college class, but I
bought all the textbooks
um for these Middle East classes. And
just to read about, you know, dynastic
succession and
and the history of the Bedouins and the
creation of first of the of the uh
the uh Trucial States and how they
became the United Arab Emirates and the
history of Saudi Arabia, which which
then led to the House of Saud, that that
tome that is the full the complete
history of Saudi Arabia. I forgot I
loved it. I didn't know that the Rashid
family controlled the peninsula before
the Saud family, and then they fought
this fight. When I was finally stationed
in Saudi Arabia and I met a member of
the Rashid family, we talked about that.
And he's like, "Yeah, imagine how I
feel. This used to be our kingdom, and
now look at us. We work for them. We
have nothing." And it was just
fascinating to me.
I loved the history. I loved the the
the mathematical construct of the
language, I loved the poetry.
And um and I the first time I went to
the Middle East, it was like, you know,
ah, finally.
Just fell in love with the place.
What's your favorite place in the Middle
East at the moment?
>> In terms of physical beauty, I don't
think anything can rival
um Oman.
The way the cliffs, 1,000-ft cliffs
crash straight down into the sea, is
just
a sight to behold.
In terms of history, and I love history,
I have never been any place as
magnificent as Damascus.
You know, you look at these things, you
look at these things in the center of
Damascus today that are mentioned in the
Bible.
That's how old they are.
And then,
you know, I spent two of the happiest
years of my life in Bahrain.
I I love Bahrain. I love the Bahraini
people. I'm still in touch with the
Crown Prince. We went to college
together.
And I I
I just can never get back enough times.
It's so wonderful.
And then, you know, you can't short
short change
Cairo and the magnificence that's Cairo
or even Jerusalem.
Incredible.
I can't get enough of it.
It is. It is. And uh
I met This was about 15 years ago. And
there was somebody who used to work very
closely with the Sultanate of Oman.
And he was from the Zawawi family. Mhm.
And uh they do and his father, I mean, I
met the son, and his father was in the
car with the with the Sultanate at the
time and there was a car crash and he
was uh unfortunately the gentleman that
died, but uh
you know,
they're so open-minded. They were taking
actually restaurants back from the UK
um to Oman to be able to
to just improve the place. And it's not
just Oman isolated.
I mean, at the time I mean he was
friends he were close friends with Garry
Kasparov and they were crafting this
amazing golden iPhone to give to him
with a chess a custom chessboard being
made. And I remember we were sitting at
the Claridge's Hotel and
and and
look, uh it it it was brilliant
memories. Uh you know, we we were having
a good chat and uh uh a good time. And
just to see the progression at that time
until
it's immense. I mean, when you look at
the rest of the Western world and how
the GCC countries are pushing forward,
it is unbelievable.
Unbelievable. Now, in most cases
Bahrain and Oman aside, it's nice to
have a bottomless pit of money. That's
great. But, you're right. Even in
Bahrain and Oman, which don't have oil
and don't have those giant incomes, the
development is absolutely astounding.
It's incredible. Why can't every Why
can't every country do this? I I don't
know.
You know, you back then when I was when
I was living there 30 years ago, um
Bahrain really didn't have anything.
And so, we would drive to uh Saudi
Arabia uh to Al Khobar or Dammam or
Dhahran to um we would go to dinner,
we'd go to the souk, we'd go to the
mall, buy some dates, whatever, drive
back across the causeway.
Um
the first time I went to Doha,
there was only one building in the
country that was more than three
stories, and that was the Marriott
Hotel.
Um otherwise, everything was made of
mud,
everything was small,
and then
this
development occurred.
And they all look like Dubai now. It's
just incredible.
There's a reason why after the the start
of the civil in Lebanon, Bahrain became
the banking center of the Middle East
because they knew exactly what to do to
attract those banks and businesses. It's
incredibly friendly. It's a an
incredibly friendly environment for
business
with the Emirates being even friendlier
and Doha being even friendlier.
So, they don't they don't really have to
have oil anymore.
It's it it doesn't matter anymore.
Do you think it's easier to do business
there? I mean, I know a lot of people
from the UK, the US, from Europe,
they've moved to Dubai, they've set up
companies in ADGM or DIFC.
And they're saying, "Look, for us to get
a license to do business in let's say
the financial sector, trading sector,
money business, it's so much easier.
They make you jump through so many hoops
over here in the States and you know,
you do one thing wrong and they're on
your case like a ton of bricks." Yes.
And and you know, money is just flowing
into the place. Why do you think that
is? What Why is there so much
bureaucratic tape in the Western world?
I mean, they're shooting themselves in
the foot. See, this is kind On one hand,
this is the price of democracy. On the
other hand,
we go through cycles where we have
socialist or or progressive governments
versus conservative governments. It goes
back and forth. Um in the West, I mean.
I've got a friend right now who's trying
to register a company in Spain. Well,
he's been trying to register this
company in Spain for the last 8 months
and just can't get it done.
Well, in in the Emirates or or in Qatar,
you could register a company in 15
minutes.
You just register. That's it. Now, the
only downside is you have to have a
local sponsor. But that's easy. That
takes 15 minutes.
So, they're just not dealing with this
history of of regulation and and
in some cases, lawfare, they just don't
have that. It's all about business.
And in Europe,
it's not about business. It's about
regulation. Yeah, I totally agree. And
that's why we could probably see all of
this rapid development over there.
Um just shifting back to your your work,
what's the dumbest or most surreal thing
that you've seen in the field? Nobody's
ever asked me that question before.
Well, I'll let you judge whether this is
dumb
or just unfortunate. But I've told this
story
a couple of times. The night that we
captured Abu Zubaydah and dozens upon
dozens of Al-Qaeda fighters.
We caught so many people that night that
we had to bring them to our safe house
for interrogation in shifts, 10 at a
time.
They would come in a in a paddy wagon
that the Pakistanis had uh
had loaned us.
And so, the first
group of 10 prisoners came in and they
were wearing hoods.
And this idiot who worked for me,
who so desperately wanted to be in
charge, and he kept talking about the
men under my command. And I would say,
"There are no men under your command.
I'm the chief here.
You are here at my invitation."
So, he brought these 10 in and I said,
"Why are they wearing hoods?"
He said, "We don't want them to see our
faces." I said, "Are you seriously
telling me that you have never read the
Geneva Convention? It is a war crime for
them to be hooded. Take the hoods off."
And he says, "Wait, don't take the hoods
off." And I said, "Oh."
I said, "You are committing a war
crime." He said, "Well, I'm going to
report you to headquarters." I said,
"I'm already reporting you to
headquarters. Take the hoods off."
And so, we took the hoods off.
We reported each other to headquarters
and I got in trouble. Why was that?
Because they didn't give a about
the Geneva Convention. Who's going to
Who's going to sue the CIA? Who's going
to have standing to sue the CIA? And
name one court anywhere in America
that's going to punish the CIA for
violating the Geneva Convention. That's
it. Was that
standard practice? I mean, in situations
like this when they're in a foreign
land,
there's going to be situations, and
correct me if I'm wrong, I'm looking at
this from a CV point of view, an
outstand outsider,
there's going to be situations where
conventions, rules,
they go out the window. Yeah. Right? And
it becomes standard practice. Where is
the line? Where is the
Where is the line in the sand? I think
the line in the sand changes
depending on who's in charge and
depending on the political environment
in Washington.
In the not just immediate post-9/11
period, but the post-9/11 period that
went well into the Obama administration.
In the decade or decade and a half after
9/11, there were no rules.
There were no rules, and we we see now
even, you know, 23 years after the
capture of Abu Zubaydah, that
that the courts don't care that there
were no rules.
The courts are still finding in favor of
the CIA.
Most recently 2 weeks ago.
Uh in the in the 9th Circuit Court of
Appeals.
So, I think that that has largely
changed.
Maybe I shouldn't even say that because
with Donald Trump, he's he's challenging
courts, and the courts are just backing
down. You know what? I don't know.
That's a tough question.
I I I used to believe that we were
that we were a country governed by the
rule of law.
And that's not really 100% true. It
wasn't at all true
immediately after 9/11.
It was just like the wild west.
With the CIA going out there grabbing
people,
killing them, rendering them,
disappearing them,
and the courts didn't care. What still
keeps you up at night? You know, to tell
you the truth, what keeps me up at night
is overly aggressive American leadership
that could result in a miscalculation or
in an unnecessary confrontation with one
of America's adversaries.
For example, I really worry about China,
not because of China,
but because of the American government
provoking China. And this is not a dig
at Donald Trump. Joe Biden was just as
guilty of this as as
Donald Trump is.
Uh and then you have the likes of of
Nancy Pelosi, for example,
going to Taiwan and announcing a major
purchase of F-35 fighter jets. Why?
Why provoke the Chinese like that?
You know, why why work to convince the
Filipinos and the Australians that the
Chinese are on the brink of it of an
invasion of those countries? When we
know that the Chinese don't have a
uh history of imperialism.
They just don't.
They have one overseas military base in
Djibouti that they share with us.
So, I worry about an American
miscalculation, especially as it relates
to China. I think we are unnecessarily
provocative to the Chinese.
Do you feel that sometimes when I watch
the news, right, personally,
I see
a lot of things. I mean, I there's
there's mainstream news like legacy
media, and then there's new form news
like, you know, Patrick Bet-David, Joe
Rogan,
um
Russell Russell
No, Russell Brand.
I've forgotten the other guy's name
anyway.
Um
Bartlett, Steven Bartlett. Sure. And
these are the largest podcasters in the
world. Right? Sure, everyone has to pick
a side, but when you're you're soaking
up all the information and you're making
a decision on what you are seeing, I
take a step back on a human level and I
say I ask myself why. Why would someone
do this? Why would a country do this? I
mean, even if you look at some of the
comments on the news YouTube videos, a
lot of people are confused asking why.
Why are we provoking this war? Why
Ukraine? Why X? Why Y? Why Z?
It doesn't make sense. The logical thing
to do would be to de-escalate and try to
use some other diplomatic measures or
strategic measures or different sciops
if they have to, which I'm sure they're
going on in the background anyway. So,
why are these blatant stupidity steps,
is what I call it, happening, John?
Please shed some light. That's a great
question and it's a question that that I
find myself
asking myself
all the time and I will admit to you
that I have consistently
um
underestimated Donald Trump.
You know, in the first term
I I
I struggled with the notion that maybe
Donald Trump was mentally ill
or was so
he was just so out of his element that
we were watching just day after day of
buffoonery.
And I think I
in part I underestimated him. In part
it took him that long to get comfortable
in the position. But I'll I'll give you
an example.
first,
right?
We know from the 1920s that these
massive tariffs don't work. If anything,
they're going to
raise inflation in the United States and
and break the economy.
But then today we hear that the CEO of
Nvidia is meeting with Trump. That
they're talking about chips for the
Chinese. We know that Trump loves these
big overarching deals that settle all
outstanding issues.
Was that the plan all along? Did we
underestimate Trump? And did we did we
think that he was pursuing uh
he was pursuing tariffs just for the
sake of pursuing tariffs or is there
really going to be a big overarching
deal with the Chinese?
It's I struggle with this.
But
maybe I've just missed it.
And he was right and I was wrong. Do you
think that comes from
I mean look, I I have
liked Donald Trump in a business sense
uh because of the art of the deal. He's
a good negotiator, he's a good
businessman, he's successful.
And when it came to politics, I think
I'm in the same boat as you. I didn't
actually understand what was going on.
I was trying to and you know, a part of
me was saying
this guy is not stupid.
Right? He's he's a clever guy.
He's not he's not coming from a
politician's perspective. He's coming as
a businessman. And a businessman, they
don't show their cards. You know, they
don't go in and say, "Hey, this is
transparency, what I'm going to do, what
I'm not going to do. This is how big the
carrot is, this is how long the stick
is." It's you keep that as a mystery as
a negotiate as as a bargaining chip.
Right? And if you've noticed everything
that he's done, he's destabilized and
brought things back together.
Destabilized and brought things back
together. So while everyone is running
around
you know, scrambling to understand what
happened, then ah some news comes out,
well oh that makes sense now.
So he's always keeping people at the
edge of their seats.
That's my analysis of him. I could be
right, I could be wrong. I don't know.
But what are your thoughts on that?
Yeah, I have to agree with you and I
don't know if if I'm right or if I'm
wrong.
You know, maybe he's
he's you know, not in his right mind,
but
you know, a broken clock is right twice
a day. But then, you know, he'll do
something like he'll bomb Iran
after president after president after
president has refused to do that.
He goes and does it at the behest of the
Israelis.
And then lo and behold,
the Iranian government announces that
it's still open to continue
negotiations.
Like, what?
Why would they do that? If anything, if
I were the president of Iran, I would
absolutely positively seek to build a
nuclear weapon now because it would be
the only thing to protect me from the
Israelis.
But no.
Now they announce, "Okay, we're ready to
resume negotiations." Absolutely
incredible. So, maybe there's something
that he knows that we don't know.
Otherwise, I can't figure out what's
happening here.
Maybe what you see what he in my mind,
it sets a new precedent because what he
knows could be good or bad, right? They
could continue to do to build whatever
they want anyway.
Maybe there was not full destruction
that day. I mean, if you knew that you
know, things were heating up, would you
or let's say your garage was going to
get robbed and you had a beautiful
classic car in there, a Porsche.
And said people keep saying, "I'm going
to come for that Porsche. I'm going to
come for that Porsche." Would you keep
it there?
You'd move it. You'd do something,
right? However, maybe I'm over over
simplifying things and maybe, yeah, it
was successful. However,
there was a retaliation, right? From
Iran. Okay, albeit a showman
retaliation, but they did something that
I didn't expect. They used a ballistic
missile
>> Yes. that the Iron Dome could not stop.
That's right. Doesn't that set a new
president or precedent saying, "Hold on
a second. You you've got an Iron Dome,
but we can get through it. But we won't.
We choose not to." In fact, that that
can be traced back even a little farther
further. Um
do you remember in the first go-round
between the Israelis and the Iranians,
um
Israelis bombed Iran and then the
Iranians uh sent drones, hundreds of
drones.
But they told the Israelis in advance,
"We're going to send drones." And then
they warned both the Iraqis and the
Jordanians, "We're going to send these
drones so they're going to overfly your
territory." And it was hundreds of them.
Seven of them got through.
Now, these were slow-motion drones.
We're not talking about hypersonic
missiles here. These are just regular
old drones.
And seven of them got through.
And that was a lesson for everybody that
this Iron Dome is actually penetrable.
And so when it came time to really fight
the Israelis,
and the Iranians chose to use ballistic
missiles, they were able to successfully
target the likes of IDF headquarters,
for example, or IDF communications, and
penetrate the dome again.
So, you know, there's been a lot of
speculation too about the the ceasefire.
I really believe the ceasefire came
about not at the request of the of the
Iranians, but at the request of the
Israelis because they were out missiles.
I think they had fired all their
missiles. You know, it's a finite
number. You're buying them from the
United States. So, it's a finite number,
and I think they just used them all.
And they couldn't continue this this
fight any longer. So, they needed
time to regroup. And they the only way
they could do that was was with a
ceasefire. And one other thing, too.
When the United States uh bombed Iran,
the Iranians, of course, in order to
save face had to respond. And so they
bombed Al Udeid airbase in uh Qatar.
But they informed the United States 2
hours 2 hours before
that they were going to
launch.
So they launched a missile. The US knew
it was coming.
At first the US said that it dropped
harmlessly in an isolated part of the uh
of the base. It turned out that wasn't
true.
Uh it hit a communications uh dome, a
geodesic dome it that housed top secret
communications. So the Iranians got
lucky.
But the US didn't respond.
The Iranians saved face.
Everybody decided, "Okay, we're all
even. Now we can move on." And so maybe
they are ready for for talks again. And
all of this happened while I think Saudi
Arabia announced that it was going to
normalize
relations with Iran, right? Just
Well, yeah. That actually started
6 months or so before um
before the uh the Gaza
operation began.
You know, the the the Saudis and
Iranians have long hated each other and
distrusted each other going back to the
Iranian Revolution in 1979.
Nobody seems to remember the takeover of
the Holy Kaaba in Mecca where Iranian uh
radicals uh that had infiltrated
the crowds attending the uh
the uh
uh Hajj
uh took over the Kaaba and
and held it. Saudi special forces
attacked. Hundreds of people were
killed. And then for years afterwards,
Iranians were banned from the Hajj.
So there's always been this distrust and
there have been periods where diplomatic
relations were cut off that lasted as
long as periods where there were
diplomatic relations. The US was always
happy about that.
Because so long as things were bad
between Saudi Arabia and Iran, the
Saudis returned to us to defend them.
Well, now things are not so bad between
Saudi Arabia and Iraq.
And they've exchanged ambassadors,
they've reopened embassies.
Um
Mohammed bin Salman
went to Tehran.
Uh Araqchi went to Riyadh. Things are
actually going pretty well.
We don't like that. And then the Saudis
were going to open relations with uh
diplomatic relations with Israel as part
of round two of the Abraham Accords. And
so in order to stop that, Hamas launched
the October 7th uh attacks.
So, it's like we're on the brink of some
kind of peace. It's a peace that does
not include the Palestinians,
which is what makes the Iranians so
angry and those of us who believe in
Palestinian human rights.
Um but the Saudis don't care.
The Israelis don't care. Donald Trump
doesn't care.
And so they want to push this whole
thing forward. If you are in I mean, how
would you resolve that? Like I I watch
Piers Morgan and I watch the debates on,
you know, majority of the major
channels.
And both sides are obviously very
passionate, right? And I'm sure both
sides can make a valid case
as to why they are fighting, right? So
deeply.
Whether it's right or wrong, right? It's
their beliefs. I mean, how would you
resolve this knowing what the two sides
are trying to do, right? I mean, how
Dennis Ross, who was the long-time
special envoy for Arab-Israeli peace.
Across presidents, George H.W. Bush,
Bill Clinton, George W. Bush.
Um
Dennis Ross says there are no new ideas.
All the ideas have been thought of. And
all of them have been rejected by one or
more parties.
So, something has to be imposed. Now,
the situation is constantly changing, so
you can't take an idea that would have
worked in 1990 and say, "Well, this this
was a good idea 1990. Let's just do it
now." It doesn't work like that. You
can't impose these ideas because the
situation on the ground constantly
changes. You know, people talk about the
debate between the one-state solution
and the two-state solution. Honestly, I
think we're looking at a three-state
solution, right? There's no connection
between Gaza and the West Bank. They
don't even like each other.
And I think that Gaza has to be some
sort of independent entity. And I think
that that the West Bank should be a free
and internationally recognized Palestine
with the East Jerusalem as its capital.
And they can work the the map like they
did in uh in January of 2001 and figure
that out. But um there's an idea being
floated now. It's been reported in the
the left-wing Israeli media that I think
could possibly be the basis for future
talks. And that is that Gaza becomes
semi-independent in that it agrees to
disarm
and it's administered by Saudi Arabia.
Right? So, there's no military uh the
Saudis would be the police force.
Gaza Palestinians would not be allowed
to to bear arms.
And then
the Saudis would build a port, an
airport, an electrical grid, a sewage
treatment facility
and get the economy started. But, it
would be Gaza for Palestinians.
And I think that that might be the basis
for future talks.
>> Do you think it's gone too far now?
Oh, I think it's gone way, way too far
on both sides.
You know, killing civilians is not going
to get you anything that you're that
you're going to be
proud of, right? It's going to get you a
missile up your ass is what it's going
to get you. And and we see I mean, what
do they expect the Israelis to do? We
know the Israelis don't respect human
rights. We know the Israelis are
perfectly happy to kill women and
children, and elderly, and blow up
hospitals, and and starve people, and
make them die of thirst. They're
perfectly happy to do that because they
don't care about human rights.
So, what did the what did Gaza
Palestinians What did Hamas think was
going to happen
after attacking this this music
festival?
Th- That
in large part they did to themselves.
I mean, I'm not excusing Israeli
atrocities, and that's what they are.
They're they're crimes against humanity
and war crimes, and Netanyahu and those
around him should be in the dock at The
Hague. Don't get me wrong.
But, with that said,
it's like
nobody should be surprised that this has
been the Israeli reaction.
Number one.
Number two,
we see what happens
when the Palestinians try to go the
peaceful route.
The Israelis
crush them
and destroy them, and steal their land,
and and take radical settlers from the
United States to resettle them. Look at
what's happening in the West Bank. It
looks like Bosnia now,
where these little islands of of Jewish
settlers completely surrounded by
historically Palestinian land. That is
absolutely unacceptable.
And so, you know,
the the Emir of Bahrain once said
uh to me, we were sitting at his beach
house,
and he said George H.W. Bush was the
last American president that gave the
Arabs a fair shake.
And I think that that's true. I think
that the Arabs have not
had a a president an American president
treat them with
equality and equanimity
since George H.W. Bush, who cut off loan
guarantees to Israel because they
wouldn't stop building settlements.
And every president since then has
kowtowed to the Israelis.
The settlements not just have to stop,
they have to go. They have to be
destroyed just like the settlements in
Sinai were destroyed when Israel
returned Sinai to Egyptians. This this
takes me back to what we spoke earlier
on about
the how, the why moment. Like you
we're watching the whole world is
watching
and the audience is probably thinking
how is this even allowed? We know it's
illegal.
It's been proven it's illegal, but how
and why is it been
let to happen? I mean, why isn't
somebody stopping this? Why are
people, leaders, world leaders, powerful
countries just standing and watching
this happen? Why? It is not possible
to overestimate the power of the Israel
lobby in the United States.
Not possible to overestimate the amount
of money that they are willing to pour
into American elections.
And so they
essentially buy seats in Congress.
And if the members of Congress who are
who are elected
don't support is Israeli line
adequately or appropriately, they are
primary and they are thrown out and
replaced with a pro-Israel
uh member of Congress. It's gotten to
the point where Yeah, I think it's
something like 70% of
congressmen and senators have have taken
AIPAC money. I think I'm pretty sure
it's 70%. It may even be higher than
70%. And I'll tell you another thing, at
the staff level and I've said this
before, but my very first week on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee staff
um
the AIPAC lobbyists came to the office
and they could not have possibly been
any more friendly.
Hi,
congratulations.
Welcome to the Foreign Relations
Committee. We would like to give you an
all expenses paid trip to the Holy Land
at not Israel. The Holy Land. And we're
going to give you a tour of all the
Christian holy sites and it's going to
knock your socks off. I said no, thanks.
I can pay for my own vacations if I want
to go to Israel.
Well,
most people in the office took the trip.
They went and then of course they feel
indebted to to AIPAC and indebted to the
Israelis for spending all this money and
everything was first-class, the finest
hotels, wonderful meals,
escorted uh
tours of all of the holy sites.
They just buy the support. But, there's
an iron fist that comes along with it
that if you don't tow the line, they
crush you. And you mentioned something
about, you know, working with different
presidents of the United States. I mean,
you were under Obama and um
Clinton.
Sorry, uh Clinton to Bush, right? And
Obama was I think the one that gave you
trouble at the time. And how was it
working for each of
these presidents? Oh, presidents had
vastly different levels of interest in
intelligence and international affairs.
George H. W. Bush, I I came in I came
into government at the very end of the
Reagan administration. And then George
H. W. Bush
not only had been vice president for
eight years,
um
but he had been CIA director
and he had been ambassador to the UN,
ambassador to China. So, he had this
deep
knowledge and understanding of
international affairs and a and a
passion for it.
So, he was fascinated by it and by what
we did and was constantly asking for
special analytic products. So, we were
in like constant communication with the
White House constantly. Bill Clinton was
briefed twice in 8 years as president.
He didn't have even a vague interest in
international affairs.
Uh Jim Woolsey, who was the CIA director
uh in the Clinton first term,
said that
not only did he never meet with the
president while he was president,
he said he wasn't sure the president
would recognize him in a meeting.
Al Gore was interested. Al Gore was
briefed 6 days a week. Al Gore was the
one who went to the Arab-Israeli peace
talks at Camp David. But, Bill Clinton
couldn't care less. Remember, it was the
economy, stupid. Remember that? Well,
you you're too young, but in 1993, that
was the the unofficial slogan. It's the
economy, stupid.
And so, that's all he cared about was
the economy, which was great throughout
the 1990s cuz he was so focused on it.
Um and then there was George W. Bush.
George W. Bush, God bless him, he
probably didn't even he couldn't even
locate these countries on a map. So, it
was it was
Dick Cheney that was in charge of uh of
international affairs and of
intelligence and defense and the Gulf
War not the Gulf War, but the Iraq War
and the Afghanistan War and all this
other stuff.
And then there was
Barack Obama, and I think Obama was a
very unique
president in that
his only qualifications were were 2
years as senator, 2 years as a senator.
He didn't know what the heck he was
doing.
And so, he was very easily manipulated
by the CIA. Did the mission change?
It always changes depending on who the
president is. Yes.
So you felt I mean did one of them make
you question whose side you were really
on? Well, yeah, George W. Bush.
Yeah.
What did he do that was different? I
mean why? You can't just have a standing
orders kill everybody.
That's just not I mean
that doesn't even mean anything. Kill
everybody. Yes, I was upset after 9/11
too, which is like everybody else was,
but as I said earlier, we're we're a
nation of laws. We're a country that's
governed by a constitution and whether
we like their politics or not, we have
to respect their their legal protections
and we didn't.
And that lessened us as a country.
So yeah, everything literally everything
changed under George W. Bush. In fact,
you know, I I worked for a deputy
director of the CIA, Jim Pavitt, who
used to say every day as a mantra, the
job of the CIA is to recruit spies to
steal secrets and to analyze those
secrets so that the president can make
the best informed policy.
On 9/12,
the CIA became a paramilitary
organization whose job it was to kill
our enemies
or to kidnap them and send them to
secret prisons to face torture.
So it changed dramatically. Why was
Clinton so nonchalant? Why didn't he Why
wasn't he briefed? Why was he out
He was a six-term
governor of Arkansas.
So he had zero
uh experience in international affairs.
When I say six-term, Arkansas was an
unusual state at the time in that the
governor was elected for a two-year
term. So every two years he came up. He
actually it six terms, he was five terms
and he lost once.
So over the course of 12 years he he
spent five terms as the governor of of
Arkansas. So for him it was all about
developing Arkansas' economy.
Al Gore on the other hand was elected to
uh the House of Representatives when he
was, you know, 30 years old. And then he
was elected to the Senate just a couple
of years later. So this was a very young
man
who was elected vice president of the
United States and through his entire
governmental career he was laser-focused
on foreign affairs, defense, and
intelligence.
And so they were actually a very good
match.
So that Clinton could focus on the
economy and Gore could focus on foreign
affairs. So it wasn't as bad as
people
make it seem. So I mean, when you first
hear, "Well, the president's only brief
been briefed twice." Right? In in in
isolation. That says one thing, right?
So Yes. to the a person listening to
that it's, "Well, he didn't know what's
going on."
Well, he didn't need to know everything
that's going on. But
>> Exactly. He needs to know what matters.
>> And and Gore, like I said, Gore was
briefed six days a week at 7:00 in the
morning. And every time there was
something important, he would brief the
president.
So, you know, we made strides. They they
were not long-lasting strides, but
strides in relations with North Korea,
for example. We came within a whisker
of actual of actual peace in the Middle
East.
under Clinton.
That was Gore driving those policies,
but Clinton endorsing them. So if if the
president needed to know something or if
the president needed to approve
something,
Gore ensured that that would Speaking
about, you know, North Korea, I mean, l-
look at the Well, what do you make of
Trump, you know,
flying over there, shaking the guy's
hand, "Hey, what's up? How you doing?
Oh, nice rockets." You know, walking
around uh nonchalant. I mean, what what
does that say to you? What Why was there
so much polarization? What was the
difference about? Trump took a lot of
heat from the foreign policy
establishment here in the United States
because he legitimized
Kim Jong-un by meeting with him.
My
view
is that that's exactly what we should be
doing.
We've had administration after
administration after administration work
so hard to not talk to our enemies, and
we accomplished nothing when we don't
talk.
So, I had no problems whatsoever with
Donald Trump engaging with the North
Koreans and meeting personally with Kim
Jong-un.
At the very least, what he accomplished
was for about 3 years,
he dialed back the risk
of
of an accidental conflict between our
two countries.
I think we should we should still be
engaging the North Koreans.
And did that change anything internally
within the CIA as well? No, it was my
understanding that the CIA was certainly
opposed to any rapprochement with with
the North Koreans, but then at the same
time, when when there are North Korean
negotiators exposed to the United
States, that opens up opportunities for
intelligence collection.
Whether purposely or or um
or in a more roundabout way.
And so, if you're if you're a CIA
operations officer, if you're the leader
of of you know, the CIA's operations
directorate, you're going to want your
officers to have access to North Korean
negotiators.
Because they're not going to be in North
Korea.
The The talks took place in Singapore,
right?
And I think the second round was where?
Vietnam or something like that? So, um
Yeah, if you're the CIA, you you want
these talks to happen. And
for the audience, for the people that
don't know your background, your job
title, and what it was. I mean, if you
could give a a snippet of what
>> Sure, sure. So, I joined the CIA in
January of 1990.
And I spent the first 7 years as as an
analyst on Iraq.
And then I switched to counterterrorism
operations, and I was there for the next
8 years.
I served overseas in Riyadh, Kuwait,
Manama,
Islamabad, Athens, and in New York at
the United Nations. I blew the whistle
on the CIA's torture program.
Later on, I went to prison for 2 years
for doing that. I would do it again
tomorrow if I had if I had to and if I
had the opportunity. I went into the
private sector for a little while, but
then went to the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee as the chief
investigator. And then for the last 10
years, I've been
a writer, an author, a commentator,
talking about these kinds of issues.
Well, that's brilliant. That's actually
commendable. I mean, you refused to
enhance interrogation techniques.
>> I was the only person who refused to be
trained in torture. Yes.
But what made you say no?
I believed strongly that it was illegal,
besides being immoral and unethical. And
it simply doesn't work.
It made us It diminished us
as as a people, as a government.
And it put us more on par with those
that we were seeking to destroy.
We got nothing out of it. If anything,
we were damaged because of it. I mean,
why did it continue for so long if it
was not working? There was a desire for
revenge after 9/11.
And
you have to remember, 9/11 was the
greatest intelligence failure in
American history. 3,000 Americans died
in one day because the CIA didn't do its
job.
And so there was this desire to just
destroy everybody. Kill as many Al-Qaeda
fighters or operatives or leaders as we
possibly could.
And um
and then those that we captured, there
was there was a desire on the one hand
to try to
uh disrupt the next attack, but on the
other hand there was a desire to make
them suffer. And about 9/11, you know,
there are all these conspiracies and
people from ex-governmental
roles coming out. I mean, this is this
is not news. It's all public
information. I mean, it was aired on the
BBC saying, "Hey, there was explosions.
No tower could fall like that." Um there
was detonations. There was another
tower. It brought the you know, one of
the
channels were broadcasting something. A
tower fell earlier or later. I mean,
what do you say to all of that? I mean,
these are credible people um coming into
the public domain saying, "We have you
know, I'm a professional uh uh
construction guy. I'm a professional
demolition expert. I have never seen a
building fall
in a vertical fashion downwards like it
did that day." I mean, what do you say
to that?
>> I'm not an engineer. I'm not an
architect. Um
but I was inside the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center
uh
in the in the year and a half
uh prior to the 9/11 attacks.
Um I know that Al-Qaeda did those
attacks. I know that Al-Qaeda flew
planes into those buildings. I don't
know
I I can't respond to, you know, the
physics of of the towers collapsing upon
themselves.
Um
I have never seen any evidence ever
that this was an inside job or that
there were explosives planted inside the
buildings.
Never have I seen any evidence. I've
heard a lot of speculation, the
speculation that you mentioned.
But I know that this was not an inside
job.
>> No, that's it. You know, it's good to
clarify that from your perspective
because it was very sad what happened.
It was a tragedy. You know, many people
lost their lives. It was horrific, you
know, for morale for the country. And I
feel that people mentioning these sort
of things, I don't know, maybe it's it's
their own version of misinformation or a
psyop. Coming back to your you the you
know, the the the whistleblowing, let's
say, right? Did you do it we mean was it
courage? Was it desperation? Was what
was it? What were you feeling at the
time?
It was not courage or desperation. It
was it was a desire to tell the truth.
The the president was lying about the
torture program. The CIA was supporting
those lies about the torture program,
and I believe that the American people
had a right to know what the country uh
what what the uh CIA rather was doing in
their name.
And so, I had the opportunity to do that
in December of 2007. And I decided to
tell the truth. I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners. I said the
torture was official US government
policy. And I said that the policy had
been personally approved by the
president.
>> And for clarity, you
you technically got charged for
revealing an identity. So, there's a
nuance there, right?
>> first I was charged with three counts of
espionage for revealing the torture
program, as well as uh one count of uh
violating the Intelligence Identities
Protection Act of 1982.
And one count of making a false
statement. We were never really sure
what the false statement was supposed to
have been.
But I hadn't committed espionage.
Talking to ABC News and the New York
Times is not espionage.
So, those espionage charges were thrown
out. Uh but yeah, I I confirmed the name
of a former colleague
uh to a reporter.
The name was never made public.
But that was the charge that they got me
on. Was there a moment before you were
about to do it? I mean, talk me through
the events leading up to that because it
was a big thing. Yeah.
>> You know, you were putting yourself on
the line. You were going against the
most powerful government in the world.
I mean,
was there a moment that you nearly said,
"You know what? I know, you know, it's
the right thing to do, but I'm not ready
to ruin my life like this or go through
what I'm about to go through." I I
really believed that I was doing the
right thing.
And
at first,
the day after my revelations, I was
surprised
at at how big of a story it was. It was
page one around the world.
That surprised me.
The FBI began investigating me at the
request of the CIA the very next day.
And they were they investigated me for a
year, and then the FBI declined to
prosecute me saying that I hadn't
committed a crime. And I really believed
the whole thing was over. It was It was
then when Barack Obama was inaugurated
that
John Brennan asked the FBI to secretly
reopen the case against me.
And then that's when they they finally
got me. Three years later. They followed
me for 3 more years. They tapped my
phones. They intercepted my emails.
And then they got
>> What was going through your mind at that
point? Because you knew this was
happening. This was like uh I mean, from
the same taking you back to your
childhood and wanting to be a spy, this
is all part of the movie.
Yeah. This is the part of the movie,
right?
>> Yeah. Yeah, you're right. Well, on the
on the one hand,
your your whole life collapses around
you, right?
Uh you don't you don't know where to
turn.
You just do what you can to survive, you
know, day by day as this as this thing
is happening to you.
But then, on the other hand,
I I believed in my heart that I was
right and they were wrong. I I I used to
say all the time, "The agency trains
you. It teaches you
that everything in life is a shade of
gray,
right?
And that's not true.
That's not true. Some things are black
and white. They're right or wrong.
And torture was simply wrong.
And so,
I decided to embrace it. And
looking at the disparity, right? You
told the truth and they locked you up
for it.
There was torture happening and they got
promotions. I mean, what does that tell
you about the system? They got more than
promotions. They got multi-million
dollar book deals
to write their memoirs.
They all got rich from this torture
program. And indeed, the two
contract psychologists who came up with
the torture program, uh James Mitchell
and Bruce Jessen,
uh
they charged the uh CIA $108 million to
to carry out this program. So, yeah, I
went to prison
and I went bankrupt and they all got
rich. What do you mean they charged $108
million to carry out Mitchell and
Jessen? What what did that mean? They
were not CIA employees. They were
contractors. They said, "Look, we came
up with this thing called enhanced
interrogation techniques. We'll We'll
train your people your people how to do
it. Uh but that'll be $108 million." And
the CIA
And the CIA wrote them a check. Do you
think what they did to you is
for national security or was that a
warning to the next guy? Oh, no, they
came right out and said
that the point wasn't to prosecute
Kiriakou.
The point was to make an example
so that if anybody else is thinking of
going public, this is what happens to
them. And you served 23 months.
23 months. Yes. And what did
prison take from you that you never got
back? Nothing.
Prison taught me things. Like I say,
I embraced it.
I embraced it. So John, you you said
prison taught you things. I mean, let
let me add something to that. What did
prison teach you that Langley never
could? Prison opened up a world
that I would never have had access to
otherwise. You know, there's this
ongoing joke that everybody in prison is
innocent. Well, you know what? A lot of
people
in prison are innocent.
We are the most overregulated, the most
overcriminalized country in the world.
We have 5% of the world's population and
25%
of the world's prison population.
We have the longest sentences for crimes
compared to our European allies.
And every year for the last 20 years,
Congress has created 50 new crimes, not
50 new laws, 50 new crimes every year.
That is something that was legal a year
ago that is now a felony today.
That's that's a problem. That doesn't
make us safer. It makes us weaker. We've
become a prison of
of we've we've become a a carceral
country
is is what it is. Why do you think that
is?
Because of the nature of our political
system where in order to win votes, you
have to appear to be tough on crime. And
the way you do that is you you create
new crimes and you increase penalties
year after year after year.
We've been doing that since
the Nixon administration. Was God ever
an influence in your life?
>> Yeah. In fact, where's my wallet? I keep
I keep a
a picture of
Saint Nectarios of Aegina
uh in my wallet, my patron saint. And um
yeah,
he was an influence. I'm I'm a
practicing Greek Orthodox Christian
and my faith has always been very
important to me.
And I knew I knew
based on the teachings of the church
fathers, the lives of the saints, I knew
that I was doing the right thing. And
one last final question is if the
younger you
the man walking into the CIA for the
first time was watching this right now,
would he be proud of who you've become?
Yeah, I think so. Yes. Yes.
You know, my ex-wife said to me one time
on a real down day,
she said, "You are
much stronger than they think you are."
And she said, "You just have to remind
yourself."
And and in the end, you know, I took the
CIA's best shot
and I came out stronger on the other
end.
If they thought this would silence me,
they didn't know me at all.
So, I came out ahead
at the end of this. John, I highly
respect you. Thank you. I had so many
more questions for you. We'll definitely
do this again. I look forward to
>> Uh this is one of many and thank you for
your time. God bless you. Thank you.